In this video series,
we take a deep dive into maximally
lowering LDL cholesterol through diet,
as LDL is the primary driver
of our primary killer
and the lower, the better.
We'll talk about expanding
the portfolio diet,
talk about plant sterols,
cholesterol-lowering supplements,
foods, herbs, spices—
you name it—
ending up with a Dr. Greger
in-the-kitchen type video
where I share how to make this
cholesterol-lowering powder
you can sprinkle on foods.
Anyway, if you don't want to wait
for each video to be released,
I've compiled all the information
into a brand new book
available at nutritionfacts.org/books.
"How to Lower Cholesterol with the Portfolio Diet"
Of the top ten
take-home messages
for the primary prevention
of cardiovascular disease,
take-home number nine
is that cholesterol-lowering
statin drugs
are considered
the first-choice drug treatment
for preventing heart disease
in those
with sufficiently elevated
LDL cholesterol,
though side effects,
like muscle pain or weakness,
may impact up to a quarter
of users.
Regardless, whether you
and your doctor decide
to start drugs,
the number one take-home message
is that the most important way
to prevent heart disease—
the number one killer
of men and women—
is to promote a healthy
lifestyle throughout life.
Enter the Portfolio Diet
for the maximal reduction
of LDL cholesterol.
There are three main
added factors in our diet
that raise LDL cholesterol:
trans fat, saturated fat,
and dietary cholesterol.
Therefore, the tolerable
upper intake levels
of these three factors
are essentially zero,
since any intake above zero
increases LDL
cholesterol concentration
and therefore increases risk
of coronary heart disease.
So, trans fat, saturated fat,
and cholesterol intake
should be as low as possible.
That means cutting back
as much as possible
on meat, dairy, eggs, and junk.
And since
partially hydrogenated oils
must be removed from
the U.S. food supply by law,
all these other uses
have been banned;
so, animal products
are now the leading source
of trans fat
in the U.S. diet as well.
Those eating a Western diet
have circulating LDL levels
around 120 milligrams
per deciliter.
No surprise, then,
that those eating plant-based
tend to have lower LDL,
with lower levels the longer
they have been eating
a whole food,
plant-based diet;
as low as 70,
but even though
that's an excellent number
compared to most people,
if you remember
from a previous video,
there really isn't
a safe cutoff.
When it comes to LDL,
the lower the longer,
the better,
even if you're at low risk.
That's where the Portfolio Diet
can come in.
By eating
a healthy plant-based diet,
you've already subtracted
all the major foods
that increase your cholesterol.
The Portfolio Diet is
a plant-based diet with a bonus,
a "portfolio" of foods—
four food types you can add
to your diet
to pull cholesterol
out of your system.
The food components include
one and a half ounces of nuts
(42 g) a day,
good sources of plant protein,
in other words, legumes,
like soy, other beans,
split-peas, chickpeas,
or lentils,
lots of food
with viscous fiber,
that's the kind of slimy fiber
found in oats, okra,
eggplant, barley,
and ground flax seeds,
and finally two grams a day
of plant sterols
from fortified foods
or supplements.
Dr. Greger is going to take
a deep dive into phytosterols;
but first, let's just see
what this diet can do.
The Portfolio Diet
was tested head-to-head
against statin treatment
plus a very low
saturated fat diet,
in a four-week randomized
controlled trial
among people
with high cholesterol.
And incredibly, those
in the Portfolio Diet group
had nearly a 30% drop
in LDL cholesterol–
similar to the 33% drop
observed in the statins
plus low saturated fat group.
Simply by emphasizing
the addition
of four dietary components
that are each likely
to contribute 4% to 7%
to overall
cholesterol reduction,
you have a diet
that reduces LDL cholesterol
with drug-like potency.
In a systematic review
and meta-analysis
of controlled trials
of the Portfolio Diet,
we still see consistent
LDL-lowering benefits,
about a 17% drop
above and beyond
the currently recommended
relatively strict
National Cholesterol
Education Program Step 2 diet,
along with lowering
of systemic inflammation
and an estimated 13% decrease
in ten-year heart disease risk.
And these results
weren't even in individuals
who all actually went
on a Portfolio Diet;
they were merely told
to eat that way.
Even just two educational
sessions over six months
telling people to adopt it
can have a significant effect.
I mentioned
the four food components,
but what does a sample menu
look like?
Nuts for snacks;
soy foods and beans
for plant protein;
oats, barley, okra, eggplant,
Metamucil, and oranges
for soluble fiber;
and what's all
this margarine for?
They were using plant
sterol-fortified margarine,
like Benecol
and Promise Activ,
formerly known as Take Control.
Yes, they have added
plant sterols,
but they're also chock-full
of salt, saturated fat,
and artificial flavors.
I mean, if you're going to use
some sort of spread,
this would be better than
non-sterol fortified margarine
or butter,
but seems like a strange way
to prevent heart disease.
Plant sterols are
naturally concentrated
in sesame seeds and wheat germ
and also found in a variety
of grains and legumes.
To get that recommended two
or three grams a day, though,
you may have to take
plant sterol supplements.
In fact, should we all
be doing that?
That's what Dr. Greger
will tackle next,
and then see
if there's any other
cholesterol-lowering supplements
that might be worth taking.
Finally,
what about all the other foods
that lower cholesterol?
What about expanding
our portfolio
to make some kind
of Portfolio Plus Diet
with as many different
cholesterol-lowering foods
and herbs and spices as we can?
Again, not as a replacement
for drugs,
but as a way to drive our LDL
as low as possible
with our fridge and pantry
in addition to anything
we might have
in our medicine cabinet.